Dr Thiago R. Oliveira

Personal Summary

I am Lecturer in the Department of Criminology at the University of Manchester. I am a quantitative criminologist who draws on theories from sociology, psychology, and social policy to investigate the relationship between exposures to policing and social outcomes. My research mostly relies on procedural justice theory, the theory of legal cynicism, and social disorganisation theory to investigate how exposure to neighbourhood characteristics and police behaviour can influence cultural perceptions about the law and legal authority using methods from quantitative social social science, causal inference, and data science.

- ♥ Williamson 4.48 Department of Criminology School of Social Sciences The University of Manchester
- thiago.oliveira@manchester.ac.uk
- ↑ ThiagoROliveira.com
- ♥ @ROliveiraT
- Google Scholar

Professional Appointments

The University of Manchester, Manchester, UK

· Sep. 2023—...: Lecturer in Policing, Department of Criminology

EDUCATION

London School of Economics and Political Science, London, UK

Ph.D., Social Research Methods, 2017 - 2021

- Supervisory team: Prof. Jonathan Jackson & Prof. Jouni Kuha
 - Thesis examiners: Prof. Jeffrey Fagan & Dr. Amy Nivette

University of São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil

M.A., Sociology, 2014 - 2016

- Visiting Scholar, International Institute for the Sociology of Law (Oñati, Spain), Fall 2015
- Award: Best M.A. dissertation concluded in the Department of Sociology in 2016

B.A., Social Sciences, 2010 - 2013

Professional Affiliations

- · 2022—present: Associate Member, Nuffield College, University of Oxford
- · 2022—present: Associate, Department of Sociology, Harvard University
- · 2017—present: Associate Member, Centre for the Study of Violence, University of São Paulo

PREVIOUS PROFESSIONAL APPOINTMENTS

University of Surrey, Guildford, UK

· Aug. 2022 - Aug. 2023: Lecturer in Criminology, Department of Sociology

University of Oxford, Oxford, UK

- · Aug. 2021 Jul. 2022: Postdoctoral Researcher, Centre for Social Investigation, Nuffield College
- · Aug. 2021 Jul. 2022: Research Fellow, Nuffield College

University College London, London, UK

- · Sep. 2020 Jun. 2021: Associate Lecturer (Teaching) in Quantitative Research Methods and Data Analysis (QStep), Department of Political Science & School of Public Policy
- \cdot Sep. 2019 Feb. 2020: Teaching Fellow in Quantitative Research Methods, Department of Political Science & School of Public Policy

University of São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil

· Apr. 2015 – Aug. 2017: Researcher, Centre for the Study of Violence

PUBLICATIONS Peer-Reviewed Papers

- Fine, Adam, Thiago R. Oliveira, Jon Jackson, Ben Bradford, Rick Trinkner, & Krisztiàn Pósch. 2024. "Did the Murder of George Floyd Damage Public Perceptions of Police and Law in the United States?" *Journal of Research in Crime and Delinquency*. (doi 10.1177/00224278241263527).
- 8. Oliveira, Thiago R. 2024. "Aggressive policing and undermined legitimacy: Assessing the impact of police stops at gunpoint on perceptions of police in São Paulo, Brazil".

 Journal of Experimental Criminology, 20: 83 121. (doi 10.1007/s11292-022-09527-9).
- 7. Suss, Joel & **Thiago R. Oliveira**. 2023. "Economic inequality and the spatial distribution of stop and search: Evidence from London". *The British Journal of Criminology*, 63(4): 828 847. (doi 10.1093/bjc/azac069).
- 6. Oliveira, Thiago R., Marcos César Alvarez, & Bruna Gisi. 2023. "From an offender-based to an offense-based justice: Changes in sentencing patterns in the juvenile justice system in São Paulo from 1990 to 2006". Crime, Law and Social Change, 79: 643 666. (doi s10611-022-10065-8
- 5. Jackson, Jonathan, Krisztián Pósch, **Thiago R. Oliveira**, Ben Bradford, Silvia Camões, Ariadne Natal, & André Zanetic. 2022. "Fear and legitimacy in São Paulo, Brazil: police-citizen relations in a high violence, high fear city". *Law & Society Review*, 56(1): 122 145. (doi 10.1111/lasr.12589)
- 4. Oliveira, Thiago R. & Jonathan Jackson. 2021. "Legitimacy, trust and legal cynicism: A review of concepts". $Tempo\ Social$, 33(3):113-145. (doi 10.11606/0103-2070.ts.2021.191381).
- 3. Oliveira, Thiago R., Jonathan Jackson, Kristina Murphy, & Ben Bradford. 2021. "Are trustworthiness and legitimacy 'hard to win, easy to lose'? A longitudinal test of the asymmetry thesis of police-citizen contact", *Journal of Quantitative Criminology*, 37:1003 1045. (doi 10.1007/s10940-020-09478-2)
- Jackson, Jonathan, Ian Bruton-Smith, Ben Bradford, Thiago R. Oliveira, Krisztián Pósch, & Patrick Sturgis. 2021. "Police legitimacy and the norm to cooperate: using a mixed effects location scale model to estimate the strength of social norms at a small spatial scale", Journal of Quantitative Criminology, 37: 547 – 572. (doi 10.1007/s10940-020-09467-5)
- 1. Oliveira, Thiago R. 2019. "Juvenile Sentencing: A Mixed-Methods Approach", Brazilian Political Science Review, 13(1). (doi 10.1590/1981-3821201900010006)

Manuscripts Under Review and Working Papers

· Oliveira, Thiago R. "Legal cynicism, intrusive policing, and the dynamics of police legitimacy: Evidence from Brazil's largest city". Preprint available at SocArXiv (https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/89jkv).

Revise & Resubmit, Law and Society Review. Revised manuscrit submitted.

· Oliveira, Thiago R., & Jonathan Jackson. "Police violence, criminal offending, and the legal socialization of adolescents".

Under review, Journal of Quantitative Criminology.

· Oliveira, Thiago R., David S. Kirk, Charles C. Lanfear, & Robert J. Sampson. "Legal cynicism and the enduring legacy of neighborhood exposures to police misconduct".

Preregistration available at OSF Registries (https://osf.io/xgeyn).

Peer-Reviewed Papers in Portuguese

6. Theodoro, Renan, Debora Piccirillo, Aline Gomes, & Thiago R. Oliveira. 2023. 'Violência como fator socializador na construção da legitimidade da polícia: um estudo com adolescentes de São Paulo, Brasil'. Análise Social, Vol. VLII(2). (doi 10.31447/AS00032573.2022243.01).

['Violence as a socialising factor shaping legitimacy: a study with adolescents from São Paulo']

 Oliveira, Thiago R., André Zanetic, & Ariadne Natal. 2020. "Preditores e impactos da legitimidade policial: testando a teoria da justeza procedimental em São Paulo", *Dados*, 63(1). (doi 10.1590/001152582020197).

['Predictors and impacts of police legitimacy: testing procedural justice theory in São Paulo']

4. Oliveira, Thiago R. André R. Oliveira, Sergio & Adorno, S. 2019. "Legitimidade policial: um modelo de mensuração", *Revista Brasileira de Ciências Sociais*, 34, 100. (doi 10.1590/3410007/2019).

['Police legitimacy: a measurement model']

3. Oliveira, Thiago R. 2017. "Mecanismos sociais de decisões judiciais: um desenho misto explicativo sobre a aplicação da medida socioeducativa de internação", *Revista Brasileira de Sociologia*, 5(10), pp. 58-88. (doi 10.20336/rbs.205).

['Social mechanisms of judicial decisions: an explanatory mixed-methods research design on juvenile sentencing']

Oliveira, Thiago R. 2017. "Oitivas cerimoniais: relatos descritivos do sistema de justiça juvenil em São Paulo", *Confluências*, 18(3), pp. 65-91. (doi 10.22409/confluências.v18i3.476).

['Ceremonial hearings: descriptive reports of the juvenile justice system in São Paulo']

Zanetic, André, Bruno Paes Manso, Ariadne Natal, & Thiago R. Oliveira. 2016.
 "Legitimidade da polícia: segurança pública para além da dissuasão", Civitas - Revista de Ciências Sociais, 16(4), pp. 148-173. (doi 10.15448/1984-7289.2016.4.24183).

['Police legitimacy: criminal policy beyond deterrence']

SELECTED PRESENTATIONS

Guest lectures

· "Como promover legitimidade das autoridades legais?" Lecture to captains of all Brazilian Military police forces, November 2022.

['Promoting the legitimacy of legal authority']

· "O que é e como promover legitimidade? Justiça procedimental e o papel da polícia na construção de crenças públicas na legitimidade das leis." *Curso NEV CAES 2022*, lecture to Brazilian police officers, June 2022 & June 2023.

['What is and how to promote police legitimacy? Procedural justice and the role of the police in shaping public beliefs about the legitimacy of the law']

- · "A legitimacy crisis among ethnic minorities? Understanding the 'defund the police' movement." Postgraduate module: *Criminal Justice Systems*, Department of Sociology, University of Surrey, March 2022.
- · "Police violence and police legitimacy: A legitimacy crisis among ethnic minorities?" Postgraduate module: *Police Violence and Racial Oppression*, Department of Sociology, University of Oxford, February 2022.
- · "Police-citizen contact and public attitudes towards legal authority: a longitudinal test of procedural justice policing." Postgraduate module: *Public Policy Analysis*, University of Minho, Portugal, May 2019.

Invited talks

- · "Causal inference with observational data?" Three Decades of Quantitative Criminology at Manchester, University of Manchester, March 2024.
- · "Legal cynicism and the enduring legacy of police misconduct." (with David S. Kirk). CrimCafe Internal Seminars, University of Manchester, March 2024.
- · "Dynamics of the overpolicing-underpolicing paradox in São Paulo." Latin American Centre, University of Oxford, March 2022.
- · "Police use of force and legal cynicism: Preliminary findings from the Project on Human Development in Chicago Neighborhoods" (with David S. Kirk). London Policing Seminar Series, University College London, December 2021.
- "Violence and coercive policing: Dynamics and consequences of the overpolicing-underpolicing paradox in Brazil's largest city." London Policing Seminar Series, University College London, October 2021.
- "Violence and coercive policing: Dynamics and consequences of the overpolicing-underpolicing paradox in Brazil's largest city." Seminário NIED-CERES, UERJ/UFRJ, Brazil, September 2021.
- · "Social conservatism and legitimacy: predicting public support for police violence in São Paulo." Workshop *Trust in Justice*, University of Minho, Portugal, September 2017.
- · "Profiling mechanisms in the Brazilian juvenile justice system." Violence, media, and youth, SESC, Brazil, June 2017

Scientific meetings

· ASC · 2019, 2020 (cancelled), 2022, 2024

· Eurocrim · 2017, 2019, 2022, 2023, 2024

 \cdot ISA \cdot 2018

 \cdot SBS (Brazil) \cdot 2015, 2017

· ANPOCS (Brazil) · 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016

AWARDS LSE Class Teacher Award

2018/2019 - LSE Class Teacher Award nominated by the Department of Methodology

Departmental Award: Best Dissertation

2017 - Best M.A. dissertation concluded in 2016 in the Department of Sociology, University of São Paulo

Conference Award: Top 3 paper

2016 - VI Political Science Graduate Seminar, University of São Paulo

GRANTS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

Travel Fund

LSE Postgraduate Travel Fund, LSE – 2018, 2019: GBP 2,000.00

PhD scholarship

LSE PhD Studentship, LSE - 2017-2021: GBP 140,000.00

M.A. scholarship

 $Bolsa\ de\ mestrado,$ National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq) – 2014-2016: BRL 36,000.00

Residence Grant

Residence Grant, International Institute for the Sociology of Law (IISL) - Nov-Dec 2015

${\bf Research\ Trainee\ (Research\ fellowship\ for\ undergraduate\ students)}$

 $Iniciação\ Científica,$ The São Paulo Research Foundation (FAPESP) – Jan-Dec 2013: BRL 7,000.00

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

The University of Manchester

- · Policing and the Police (CRIM20051). Course unit director (2023/24, 2024/25). Year 2.
- · Modelling Criminological Data (CRIM20452). Course unit director (2023/24, 2024/25). Year 2.
- · Data Analysis with R (CRIM70821). Lecturer (2023/24). PGT.

University of Surrey

- · Measuring the Social World: Quantitative Methods (SOC1050). Module leader (2022/23). Year 1.
- · Advanced Quantitative Methods (SOC2093). Lecturer (2022/23). Year 2.
- · Crime and Society (SOC1034). Lecturer (2022/23). Year 1.

50th GESIS Spring Seminar

· Causal Inference in Observational Studies. Co-lecturer (2021). MSc/PhD.

University College London (UCL)

- · Data Analysis (QStep) (POLS0010). Class Teacher (2021). Year 2.
- · Introduction to Quantitative Methods (PUBL0055). Class Teacher (2019, 2020). MSc.

London School of Economics and Political Science (LSE)

- · Introduction to Quantitative Methods for Media and Communications (MY464). Co-lecturer (2020). MSc.
- · Introduction to R Programming (MY591). Instructor (2019). MSc/PhD.
- · Mutivariate Analysis and Measurement (MY455). Graduate Teaching Assistant (2019). Msc/PhD.
- · Intermediate Quantitative Methods (MY465). Class Teacher (2017, 2018). MSc.
- · Introduction to Quantitative Analysis (MY451). Graduate Teaching Assistant (2017). MSc.

University of São Paulo (USP)

- · Research Methods and Techniques (FSL0203). Graduate Teaching Assistant (2015, 2017). Year 1.
- Prison in Modern Society (FSL0531). Undergraduate Teaching Assistant (2013). Years 3/4.

Supervisory Experience

The University of Manchester

- · MA dissertation supervision (MA in Criminology): 2 students.
- · Undergraduate dissertation supervision (BA in Criminology): 9 students.

University of Surrey

- · MSc dissertation supervision (MSc in Criminology): 1 student.
- · Undergraduate dissertation supervision (BSc in Criminology, BSc in Sociology, BSc in Sociology and Criminology): <u>6 students</u>.
- · Personal Tutor (undergraduate, postgraduate, and exchange students): 18 students.

University of Oxford

- · UNIQ+ (research internship for students from under-represented and disadvantaged backgrounds).
 - Sulaiman Iqbal (2022), 'Stop and search and the Muslim populations in London'

Reviewer

Reviews in English

Crime Science, Criminal Justice and Behavior, Criminology & Criminal Justice, Criminology & Public Policy, Critical Criminology, European Journal on Criminal Policy and Research, Home Office, Humanities & Social Sciences Communications, International Criminology, Journal of Contemporary Criminal Justice, Journal of Developmental and Life-Course Criminology, Journal of Experimental Criminology, Journal of Research in Crime and Delinquency, Latin American Research Review, PLOS One, Revista Salud Bosque, Victims and Offenders, Youth Justice.

Reviews in Portuguese

Dados: Revista de Ciências Sociais, Revista Brasileira de Ciências Sociais, Revista de Ciências Sociais, Revista Eletrônica de Ciência Política, Revista Estudios Sociológicos, Tempo Social.

Professional Services

Department of Criminology, University of Manchester

· Employability Lead (2024 – present)

Department of Sociology, University of Surrey

- · International Officer (Exchange Coordinator & Director of Internationalisation) (2022 2023)
- · Academic Integrity Team (2022 2023)

Public interest

- · Member of the Social Statistics Section, Royal Statistical Society (2024-present)
- · Voluntary Consultant in Research and Data Analysis at StopWatch (2020 2022)
- Member of the Advisory Board, National Survey on Violence Against Children, Fundação José Luiz Egydio Setúbal (2021 – 2022)

Student services

- · Coordinator of the LSE Quantitative Methods Reading Group (2020 2021)
- · PhD representative for the Teaching Committee, Department of Methodology, London School of Economics and Political Science (2018/2019)
- · Elected Graduate Student Representative in the Department of Sociology, University of São Paulo (2015)
- · Member of **Editorial Board** for **Primeiros Estudos** (journal organised by USP undergraduate students in Social Sciences) (2013 2014)

Computer

Statistics

SKILLS

R (proficient user and instructor), Mplus (proficient user), Stata (instructor), SPSS (instructor)

Miscellaneous

LATEX, RMarkdown, git

LANGUAGES

English (fluent), Portuguese (native), Spanish (intermediate)

August 30, 2024